<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Poemas en prosa</title>
                <author>Oscar Wilde</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Traducción</resp>
                    <name>Semillero de Poética y traducción</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Codificación y transcripción digital</resp>
                    <name>Semillero de Poética y traducción</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Modelación de datos y codificación</resp>
                    <name>Cristian Suárez-Giraldo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Revisión de texto</resp>
                    <name>Yenny Correa León</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Universidad EAFIT</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medellín</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                        Distribuida bajo Licencia Creative Commons
                        Atribución-NoComercial-CompartirIgual 4.0 Internacional (CC BY-NC-SA
                        4.0)</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title/>
                    <textLang mainLang="es" otherLangs="pt"/>
                    <relatedItem type="translatedFrom">
                        <bibl>
                            <textLang mainLang="en"/>
                            <ref target="https://www.wilde-online.info/poems-in-prose.html">Poems in
                                Prose</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <document>
        <column>
            <head>The Teacher of Wisdom</head>
            <content>
                <p rend="indent-first">From his childhood he had been as one filled with the perfect knowledge of <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, and even while he was yet but a lad many of
                    the saints, as well as certain holy women who dwelt in the free city of his
                    birth, had been stirred to much wonder by the grave wisdom of his answers.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And when his parents had given him the robe and the ring of
                    manhood he kissed them, and left them and went out into the world, that he might
                    speak to the world about <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>. For there were at
                    that time many in the world who either knew not <rs type="name" key="GGOD6">God</rs> 
                    at all, or had but an incomplete knowledge of Him, or worshipped
                    the false gods who dwell in groves and have no care of their worshippers.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he set his face to the sun and journeyed, walking
                    without sandals, as he had seen the saints walk, and carrying at his girdle a
                    leathern wallet and a little water-bottle of burnt clay.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And as he walked along the highway he was full of the joy
                    that comes from the perfect knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>,
                    and he sang praises unto <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> without ceasing;
                    and after a time he reached a strange land in which there were many cities.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he passed through eleven cities. And some of these
                    cities were in valleys, and others were by the banks of great rivers, and others
                    were set on hills. And in each city he found a disciple who loved him and
                    followed him, and a great multitude also of people followed him from each city,
                    and the knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> spread in the whole
                    land, and many of the rulers were converted, and the priests of the temples in
                    which there were idols found that half of their gain was gone, and when they
                    beat upon their drums at noon none, or but a few, came with peacocks and with
                    offerings of flesh as had been the custom of the land before his coming.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Yet the more the people followed him, and the greater the
                    number of his disciples, the greater became his sorrow. And he knew not why his
                    sorrow was so great. For he spake ever about <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, 
                    and out of the fulness of that perfect knowledge of <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">God</rs> which <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> had Himself
                    given to him.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And one evening he passed out of the eleventh city, which
                    was a city of <rs type="country">Armenia</rs>, and his disciples and a great crowd of people followed
                    after him; and he went up on to a mountain and sat down on a rock that was on
                    the mountain, and his disciples stood round him, and the multitude knelt in the
                    valley.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he bowed his head on his hands and wept, and said to his
                    Soul, "Why is it that I am full of sorrow and fear, and that each of my
                    disciples is an enemy that walks in the noonday?".</p> 
                <p rend="indent-first">And his Soul answered him and
                    said, "<rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> filled thee with the perfect
                    knowledge of Himself, and thou hast given this knowledge away to others. The
                    pearl of great price thou hast divided, and the vesture without seam thou hast
                    parted asunder. He who giveth away wisdom robbeth himself. He is as one who
                    giveth his treasure to a robber. Is not <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>
                    wiser than thou art? Who art thou to give away the secret that <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">God</rs> hath told thee? I was rich once, and thou hast made me
                    poor. Once I saw <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, and now thou hast hidden
                    Him from me".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he wept again, for he knew that his Soul spake truth to
                    him, and that he had given to others the perfect knowledge of <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">God</rs>, and that he was as one clinging to the skirts of God,
                    and that his faith was leaving him by reason of the number of those who believed
                    in him.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he said to himself, "I will talk no more about <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>. He who giveth away wisdom robbeth
                    himself".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And after the space of some hours his disciples came near
                    him and bowed themselves to the ground and said, "Master, talk to us about <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, for thou hast the perfect knowledge of <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, and no man save thee hath this
                    knowledge".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he answered them and said, "I will talk to you about all
                    other things that are in heaven and on earth, but about <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">God</rs> I will not talk to you. Neither now, nor at any time,
                    will I talk to you about <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And they were wroth with him and said to him, "Thou hast led
                    us into the desert that we might hearken to thee. Wilt thou send us away hungry,
                    and the great multitude that thou hast made to follow thee?".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And he answered them and said, "I will not talk to you about
                    <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the multitude murmured against him and said to him,
                    "Thou hast led us into the desert, and hast given us no food to eat. Talk to us
                    about <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> and it will suffice us".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">But he answered them not a word. For he knew that if he
                    spake to them about <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> he would give away his
                    treasure.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And his disciples went away sadly, and the multitude of
                    people returned to their own homes. And many died on the way.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And when he was alone he rose up and set his face to the
                    moon, and journeyed for seven moons, speaking to no man nor making any answer.
                    And when the seventh moon had waned he reached that desert which is the 
                    <rs type="place" key="DGR6">desert of the Great River</rs>. And having found a cavern in which a Centaur had once dwelt,
                    he took it for his place of dwelling, and made himself a mat of reeds on which
                    to lie, and became a <rs type="person" key="HER6">hermit</rs>. And every hour the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> praised <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">God</rs> that He had suffered him to keep some knowledge of Him
                    and of His wonderful greatness.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Now, one evening, as the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> was seated before the cavern
                    in which he had made his place of dwelling, he beheld a <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young man</rs> of evil and <!--¿young man o young?-->
                    beautiful face who passed by in mean apparel and with empty hands. Every evening
                    with empty hands the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young man</rs> passed by, and every morning he returned with his
                    hands full of purple and pearls. For he was a Robber and robbed the caravans of
                    the merchants.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> looked at him and pitied him. But he spake
                    not a word. For he knew that he who speaks a word loses his faith.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And one morning, as the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young man</rs> returned with his hands
                    full of purple and pearls, he stopped and frowned and stamped his foot upon the
                    sand, and said to the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>: “Why do you look at me ever in this manner as I
                    pass by? What is it that I see in your eyes? For no man has looked at me before
                    in this manner. And the thing is a thorn and a trouble to me”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> answered him and said, “What you see in my
                    eyes is pity. Pity is what looks out at you from my eyes”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young man</rs> laughed with scorn, and cried to the
                    <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> in a bitter voice, and said to him, “I have purple and pearls in my
                    hands, and you have but a mat of reeds on which to lie. What pity should you
                    have for me? And for what reason have you this pity?”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">"I have pity for you", said the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>, "because you have no
                    knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">"Is this knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> a
                    precious thing?" asked the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young man</rs>, and he came close to the mouth of the
                    cavern.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">"It is more precious than all the purple and the pearls of
                    the world", answered the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">"And have you got it?" said the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs>, and he came
                    closer still.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">"Once, indeed", answered the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>, "I possessed the
                    perfect knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>. But in my foolishness
                    I parted with it, and divided it amongst others. Yet even now is such knowledge
                    as remains to me more precious than purple or pearls".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And when the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> heard this he threw away the
                    purple and the pearls that he was bearing in his hands, and drawing a sharp
                    sword of curved steel he said to the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>, "Give me, forthwith this knowledge
                    of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> that you possess, or I will surely slay
                    you. Wherefore should I not slay him who has a treasure greater than my
                    treasure?".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> spread out his arms and said, "Were it not
                    better for me to go unto the uttermost courts of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs> 
                    and praise Him, than to live in the world and have no knowledge of
                    Him? Slay me if that be your desire. But I will not give away my knowledge of
                    <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> knelt down and besought him, but the
                    <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> would not talk to him about <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, nor give
                    him his Treasure, and the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> rose up and said to the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>, "Be it as
                    you will. As for myself, I will go to the City of the Seven Sins, that is but
                    three days journey from this place, and for my purple they will give me
                    pleasure, and for my pearls they will sell me joy". And he took up the purple
                    and the pearls and went swiftly away.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> cried out and followed him and besought him.
                    For the space of three days he followed the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> on the road and
                    entreated him to return, nor to enter into the City of the Seven Sins.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And ever and anon the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> looked back at the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs>
                    and called to him, and said, "Will you give me this knowledge of <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">God</rs> which is more precious than purple and pearls? If you
                    will give me that, I will not enter the city".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And ever did the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> answer, “All things that I have I
                    will give thee, save that one thing only. For that thing it is not lawful for me
                    to give away”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And in the twilight of the third day they came nigh to the
                    great scarlet gates of the City of the Seven Sins. And from the city there came
                    the sound of much laughter.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> laughed in answer, and sought to knock
                    at the gate. And as he did so the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> ran forward and caught him by the
                    skirts of his raiment, and said to him: "Stretch forth your hands, and set your
                    arms around my neck, and put your ear close to my lips, and I will give you what
                    remains to me of the knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>". And the
                    <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs> stopped.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And when the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> had given away his knowledge of <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>, he fell upon the ground and wept, and a
                    great darkness hid from him the city and the <rs type="person" key="JOR6">young Robber</rs>, so that he saw them
                    no more.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">And as he lay there weeping he was ware of One who was
                    standing beside him; and He who was standing beside him had feet of brass and
                    hair like fine wool. And He raised the <rs type="person" key="HER6">Hermit</rs> up, and said to him: "Before this
                    time thou hadst the perfect knowledge of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>.
                    Now thou shalt have the perfect love of <rs type="name" key="GOD6">God</rs>.
                    Wherefore art thou weeping?". And he kissed him.</p>
            </content>
        </column>
        <column>
            <head>El que enseña sabiduría</head>
            <content>
                <p rend="indent-first">Desde su infancia fue como uno que ha sido colmado del perfecto conocimiento de
                    <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, e incluso cuando era apenas un niño
                    muchos de los santos, así como algunas santas mujeres que vivían en su ciudad
                    natal, se maravillaban con la grave sabiduría de sus respuestas.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y cuando sus padres le entregaron la túnica y el anillo de
                    la adultez, él los besó y los abandonó, y salió a recorrer el mundo, para poder
                    hablarle al mundo sobre <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, porque en ese
                    tiempo había muchos en el mundo que no sabían nada de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, 
                    o que tenían un conocimiento incompleto de Él, o que adoraban
                    dioses falsos que habitan en las arboledas y a los que no les importaban sus
                    devotos.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y entonces expuso su rostro al sol y viajó, caminando sin
                    sandalias, como había visto que lo hacían los santos, cargando en su cinto una
                    cartera de cuero y una cantimplora con agua hecha de arcilla quemada.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y mientras andaba por el camino iba lleno del júbilo que
                    proviene del perfecto conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, y le
                    cantaba alabanzas a <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> sin cesar; y después de
                    un tiempo llegó a una tierra desconocida en la que había muchas ciudades.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y pasó por once ciudades. Algunas ciudades estaban en
                    valles, y otras junto a las orillas de grandes ríos, y otras estaban situadas
                    sobre colinas. Y en cada ciudad encontró un discípulo que lo amaba y que lo
                    seguía, y una gran multitud de personas de cada ciudad también lo siguió, y el
                    conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> se esparció por toda la
                    tierra, y muchos de los gobernantes se convirtieron, y los sacerdotes de los
                    templos en los que había ídolos vieron cómo se esfumaba la mitad de sus
                    ganancias, y cuando golpeaban sus tambores al mediodía nadie, o apenas unos
                    pocos, venían con pavorreales y ofrendas de carne, como era la costumbre en esa
                    tierra antes de que él llegara.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Sin embargo, cuanta más gente lo seguía y mayor era el
                    número de sus discípulos, mayor era su tristeza. Y él no entendía por qué era tan
                    grande su tristeza. Porque él siempre hablaba sobre <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> 
                    desde esa plenitud del conocimiento perfecto de <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs> que el mismo <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> le
                    había dado.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y una tarde atravesó la undécima ciudad, que era una ciudad
                    de <rs type="country">Armenia</rs>, y sus discípulos y una gran multitud lo siguieron; y él subió a una
                    montaña y se sentó en una roca de esa montaña, y sus discípulos se quedaron de
                    pie junto a él, y la multitud se arrodilló en el valle.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y hundiendo la cabeza entre sus manos lloró, y dijo a su
                    alma: “¿Por qué es que estoy lleno de tristeza y de miedo, y por qué cada uno de
                    mis discípulos es como un enemigo que camina a plena luz del día?”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y su alma le contestó diciendo: “<rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> 
                    te colmó del perfecto conocimiento de sí mismo, y tú entregaste
                    ese conocimiento a otros. Repartiste la perla preciosa e hiciste girones el
                    manto sin costuras. Aquel que entrega sabiduría se roba a sí mismo; es como
                    aquel que entrega su fortuna a un ladrón. ¿Acaso <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> 
                    no es más sabio que tú? ¿Quién eres tú para entregar el secreto
                    que <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> te ha contado a ti? Yo era rica y tú me
                    hiciste pobre. Yo vi a <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> y ahora tú hiciste
                    que Él se oculte de mí”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y volvió a llorar, porque sabía que su alma decía la verdad,
                    y que él había dado a otros el perfecto conocimiento de <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, y que él ahora era como quien se aferra a las faldas
                    de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, y que su fe lo iba abandonando a medida
                    que crecían en número aquellos que creían en él.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y se dijo a sí mismo: “Yo no hablaré más acerca de <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>. Aquel que da sabiduría se roba a sí
                    mismo”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y al cabo de unas horas, sus discípulos se le acercaron y se
                    plegaron hasta el suelo y dijeron: “Maestro, háblanos de <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, porque tú tienes el perfecto conocimiento de <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, y ningún otro hombre salvo tú tiene este
                    conocimiento”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y él les respondió diciendo: “Yo les hablaré de todas las
                    otras cosas que hay en el cielo y en la tierra, pero de <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs> ya no les hablaré, ni ahora ni nunca más les hablaré yo
                    de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y ellos, enfurecidos contra él, dijeron: “Tú nos trajiste al
                    desierto para que te escuchemos. ¿Nos harás partir hambrientos a nosotros y a la
                    multitud que hiciste que te siga?”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y él les contestó diciendo: “Yo no les hablaré de <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y la multitud murmuró en su contra y dijo: “Tú nos has
                    traído al desierto y no nos has dado comida para alimentarnos. Háblanos de <rs
                    type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> y eso nos dejará satisfechos”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Pero él no les respondió con ninguna palabra, porque sabía
                    que si les hablaba de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> estaría entregando su
                    tesoro.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y sus discípulos se alejaron entristecidos, y la multitud
                    regresó a sus casas. Y muchos murieron en el camino.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y cuando estuvo solo, se levantó y expuso su rostro a la
                    luna, y viajó durante siete lunas, sin hablar con ningún hombre ni responder
                    preguntas. Y cuando la séptima luna menguaba llegó a un desierto, que es el
                    <rs type="place" key="DGR6">desierto del Gran Río</rs>. Y al encontrar una caverna en la que antes habitara un
                    centauro, la tomó como su morada, se hizo una estera de ramas para tenderse y se
                    convirtió en <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>. Y a cada hora el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> alababa a <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs> por haberle permitido conservar algo del conocimiento
                    de Sí mismo y de su maravillosa grandeza.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y, una noche, cuando el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> estaba sentado frente a la
                    caverna en que había hecho su morada, contempló a un <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven</rs> de cara malvada y
                    hermosa que pasó con fea vestimenta y las manos vacías. Y todas las noches el
                    <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven</rs> pasaba con las manos vacías, y todas las mañanas volvía a pasar con las
                    manos llenas de telas color púrpura y perlas. Porque era un Ladrón y robaba las
                    caravanas de los mercaderes.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> lo miraba y sentía compasión de él. Pero no
                    dijo una sola palabra, porque sabía que aquel que habla pierde su fe.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y una mañana, mientras el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven</rs> regresaba con sus manos
                    llenas de telas color púrpura y perlas, se detuvo, y frunciendo el ceño y
                    pisando fuerte la arena con su pie, le dijo al <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>: “¿Por qué siempre me
                    miras de esta manera cuando paso por aquí? ¿Qué es eso que veo en tus ojos?
                    Porque ningún hombre me ha mirado así antes. Y esto es una molestia que me
                    aqueja y es como una espina para mí”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> le respondió diciendo: “Lo que ves en mis ojos
                    es compasión. Es la compasión que desde mis ojos te mira”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven</rs> rio con desprecio, y gritándole al <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>, con
                    voz amarga, le dijo: “Yo tengo telas de color púrpura y perlas en mis manos, y
                    tú no tienes sino una estera de ramas sobre la cual acostarte. ¿Qué compasión
                    podrías sentir tú de mí? ¿Y por qué razón sentirías tú esa compasión?”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">“Yo siento compasión de ti”, dijo el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>, “porque tú no
                    tienes ningún conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">“¿Es acaso ese conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> 
                    una cosa preciosa?”, preguntó el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven</rs>, acercándose a la boca de
                    la caverna.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">“Es más precioso que todas las telas color púrpura y todas
                    las perlas del mundo”, contestó el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">“¿Y tú lo tienes?”, preguntó el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> y se acercó más <!--¿Etiquetamos juntas las palabras <rs type="person">joven Ladrón</rs>?-->
                    todavía.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">“Lo tuve, sí”, contestó el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>, “Yo poseí el perfecto
                    conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>. Pero en mi estupidez me
                    desprendí de él y lo compartí con otros. Y, sin embargo, el conocimiento que me
                    queda sigue siendo para mí más precioso que las telas color púrpura o las
                    perlas".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y cuando el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven</rs> Ladrón oyó esto arrojó las telas color <!--Igual aquí.-->
                    púrpura y las perlas que cargaba en sus manos y, desenfundando una afilada
                    espada de acero curvado, dijo al <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>: “Dame en este instante ese
                    conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> que posees, o seguro te
                    mataré. ¿Crees que no he de matar a quien tiene un tesoro mayor que el
                    mío?”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> extendió los brazos y dijo: “¿Crees que no
                    sería mejor para mí ir a las más elevadas cortes de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> 
                    y alabarlo, que vivir en este mundo sin tener ningún conocimiento
                    de Él? Mátame si es eso es lo que deseas. Pero yo no entregaré mi conocimiento
                    de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> se arrodilló suplicándole, pero el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>
                    no quiso hablarle de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, ni entregarle su
                    tesoro, y el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> se levantó y le dijo : “Sea como tú quieres. Por mi
                    parte, iré a la <rs type="place">Ciudad de los Siete Pecados</rs>, que queda tan solo a tres días de
                    viaje desde aquí, y por mis telas color púrpura me darán placer, y por mis
                    perlas me venderán alegría”. Y levantando las telas color púrpura y las perlas
                    se marchó rápidamente.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> gritó, siguiéndolo y suplicándole. Durante tres
                    días el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> siguió al <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> por la carretera intentando persuadirlo
                    de que regresara y de que no entrase en la <rs type="place">Ciudad de los Siete Pecados</rs>.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y cada vez que el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> volvía la mirada al <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>,
                    llamándolo, le decía: “¿Me darás el conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs> 
                    que es más precioso que las telas color púrpura y las perlas? Si
                    tú me lo das, yo no entraré en la ciudad".</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y cada vez el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> contestaba: “Todo lo que tengo te lo
                    daré, salvo esa única cosa. Porque esa cosa no me es lícito entregarla”.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y en el crepúsculo del tercer día se acercaron a las grandes
                    puertas escarlata de la <rs type="place">Ciudad de los Siete Pecados</rs>. Y desde adentro de la
                    ciudad llegaba el ruido de muchas risas.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> respondió riendo también, y se dispuso a
                    tocar la puerta. Y mientras lo hacía, el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> corrió hasta él y lo agarró de
                    las faldas de su túnica, y le dijo: “Extiende tus manos y abrázame por el
                    cuello, y pon tu oído cerca a mis labios, y te daré lo que me queda del
                    conocimiento de <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>”. Y el <rs type="person" key="JOR6">joven Ladrón</rs> se
                    detuvo.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y cuando el <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs> había entregado todo su conocimiento de
                    <rs type="name" key="GOD6">Dios</rs>, cayó al suelo y lloró, y una densa
                    oscuridad cubrió la ciudad y al <rs type="person" key="JOR6">Ladrón</rs>, para que él ya no pudiera verlos.</p>
                <p rend="indent-first">Y mientras estaba tendido y llorando, sintió la presencia de
                    alguien que estaba de pie junto a él; y el que estaba de pie junto a él tenía
                    los pies de cobre y sus cabellos eran finos como la lana. Y levantando al
                    <rs type="person" key="HER6">Eremita</rs>, le dijo: “Otrora tenías el conocimiento perfecto de <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs>. Ahora tendrás el perfecto amor de <rs type="name"
                    key="GOD6">Dios</rs>. ¿Por qué lloras entonces?”. Y lo besó.</p>
            </content>
        </column>
    </document>
</TEI>
